Hi, kids.
مرحبا يا أطفال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm 71.
عُمري واحد وسبعون عامًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
My husband is 76.
زوجي ستة وسبعون عامًا.
My parents are in their late 90s,
والداي في أواخر التسعينات.
and Olivia, the dog, is 16.
وأوليفيا (الجرو) عمرها 16 سنة.
So let's talk about aging.
لذلك، لنتحدث عن الشيخوخة.
Let me tell you how I feel
دعوني أخبركم كيف أشعر
when I see my wrinkles in the mirror
عندما أشاهد تجاعيد وجهي في المرآة،
and I realize that some parts of me have dropped
وأدرك أن بعض أجزائي سقطت
and I can't find them down there.
ولا أستطيع إيجادها هناك في الأسفل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Mary Oliver says in one of her poems,
(ماري أوليفر) قالت في واحدة من قصائدها:
"Tell me, what is it that you plan to do
"أخبرني ما تخطط لفعله
with your one wild and precious life?"
في حياتك الجامحة والثمينة؟"
Me, I intend to live passionately.
بالنسبة لي، أنوي أن أعيش بشكل عاطفي.
When do we start aging?
متى نبدأ الشيخوخة؟
Society decides when we are old,
المجتمع يقرر متى نصبح كبارًا،
usually around 65, when we get Medicare,
عادةَ في الخامسة والستين، عندما نحصل على الرعاية الطبية الخاصة بكبار السن.
but we really start aging at birth.
لكننا في الحقيقة نبدأ نكبر منذ الولادة.
We are aging right now,
نحن نكبر الآن.
and we all experience it differently.
ونختبر هذا -جميعًا- بشكل مختلف.
We all feel younger than our real age,
نشعر جميعًا بأننا أصغر من عُمرنا الحقيقي؛
because the spirit never ages.
لأن الروح لا تكبر أبدًا.
I am still 17.
ما زلت في السابعة عشر من عمري.
Sophia Loren. Look at her.
أنظروا إلى صوفيا لورين.
She says that everything you see
تقول أن كل ما تشاهدونه
she owes to spaghetti.
هي مدينة به للمعكرونة.
I tried it and gained 10 pounds
لقد جربت ذلك وزدت عشرة أرطال
in the wrong places.
في الأماكن الخاطئة.
But attitude, aging is also attitude and health.
لكن الشيخوخة أيضًا حالة عقلية وصحية.
But my real mentor in this journey of aging
لكن معلمي الخاص في هذه الرحلة من الكبر في السن،
is Olga Murray.
هي (أولجا موراي).
This California girl at 60
هذه الفتاة من كاليفورنيا، وعمرها ستون عام،
started working in Nepal to save young girls
بدأت العمل في (نيبال) لتنقذ الفتيات الصغيرات
from domestic bondage.
من العبودية المحلية.
At 88, she has saved 12,000 girls,
أنقذت 12.000 فتاة ببلوغها 88 عام،
and she has changed the culture in the country.
وغيرت ثقافة بلدتها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now it is illegal for fathers
الآن، أصبح غير قانونيا للآباء
to sell their daughters into servitude.
أن يبيعوا بناتهم للعبودية.
She has also founded orphanages
وأنشأت أيضًا دورا للأيتام،
and nutritional clinics.
وعيادات غذائية.
She is always happy
إنها دائمًا سعيدة
and eternally young.
وشابة إلى الأبد.
What have I lost in the last decades?
ماذا فقدت في العقود الأخيرة؟
People, of course,
الناس -بالطبع-
places, and the boundless energy of my youth,
الأماكن، وطاقتي الشبابية التي لا حدود لها،
and I'm beginning to lose independence,
وبدأت أفقد الاستقلالية
and that scares me.
وهذا يخيفني.
Ram Dass says that dependency hurts,
يقول رام داس: “التبعية تؤلم،
but if you accept it, there is less suffering.
لكن إذا قبلتها فستكون هناك معاناة أقل."
After a very bad stroke,
بعد جلطة دماغية سيئة جدًا.
his ageless soul watches the changes
شاهدت روحه دائمة الشباب التغيرات
in the body with tenderness,
في الجسم بشفافية،
and he is grateful to the people who help him.
وهو مُمتن للناس الذين يساعدوه.
What have I gained?
ماذا كسبت؟
Freedom: I don't have to prove anything anymore.
الحرية: ليس عليَّ أن ًاثبت أي شيء بعد الآن.
I'm not stuck in the idea of who I was,
لست عالقة في فكرة من كنت في الماضي،
who I want to be,
أو من سأكون مستقبلًا،
or what other people expect me to be.
أو ما يتوقع الناس مني أن أصبحه.
I don't have to please men anymore,
ليس عليّ أن أُرضي الرجال بعد الآن
only animals.
سأٌرضي الحيوانات فقط.
I keep telling my superego to back off
أُخبرُ الأنا الأعلى بأن يتراجع،
and let me enjoy what I still have.
ويدعني أستمتع بما تبقى لي من أشياء.
My body may be falling apart,
ربما يكون جسدي قد تهاوى،
but my brain is not, yet.
ولكن ليس عقلي.
I love my brain.
أحبُ عقلي.
I feel lighter.
أشعر بأنني أخف وزنًا.
I don't carry grudges, ambition, vanity,
لا أحمل الضغائن والطموح والغرور.
none of the deadly sins that are not even
ولا أيا من الخطايا المميتة
worth the trouble.
التي لا تستحق حتى العناء.
It's great to let go.
من العظيم أن نتركها.
I should have started sooner.
كان عليا أن أبدأ عاجلًا.
And I also feel softer
وأشعر أيضًا بأنّني أكثر ليونة؛
because I'm not scared of being vulnerable.
لأنّني لا أخشى كوني عُرضة للنقد أو الجرح.
I don't see it as weakness anymore.
من الآن فصاعدًا، لا أرى ذلك كضعف.
And I've gained spirituality.
لقد ازددت روحانية.
I'm aware that before,
أنا مُدركة أن الموت كان من قبل
death was in the neighborhood.
في الحي الذي أسكُن فيه.
Now, it's next door, or in my house.
الآن، فهو بالبيت المجاور أو في منزلي.
I try to live mindfully
أحاولُ أن أعيش بانتباه.
and be present in the moment.
وأكون موجودة في الوقت الراهن.
By the way, the Dalai Lama
بالمناسبة، (الدالاي لاما)
is someone who has aged beautifully,
هو شخص كبرَ بجمال.
but who wants to be vegetarian and celibate?
لكنه من يريد أن يكون نباتيًا ولا يمارس الجنس؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Meditation helps.
التأمل يساعد.
(Video) Child: Ommm. Ommm. Ommm.
(فيديو) طفل: أوم أوم أوم.
Isabel Allende: Ommm. Ommm. There it is.
إيزابيل أليندي: أوم أوم. ها هي ذي.
And it's good to start early.
ومن الجيد البدء باكرًا.
You know, for a vain female like myself,
بالنسبة لامرأة عقيمة مثلي،
it's very hard to age in this culture.
من الصعب أن تكبر في ظل هذه الثقافة.
Inside, I feel good, I feel charming, seductive, sexy.
أشعر في داخلي أنّني بخير، فاتنة، جذابة، مثيرة.
Nobody else sees that. (Laughter)
لا أحد غيري يلاحظ ذلك.
I'm invisible.
أنا غير مرئية.
I want to be the center of attention.
أُريد أن أكون مركز الاهتمام.
I hate to be invisible.
أكره أن أكون غير مرئية.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
This is Grace Dammann.
هذه جريس دامان.
She has been in a wheelchair for six years
كانت على كرسي متحرك لمدة ست سنوات،
after a terrible car accident.
بعد حادث سيارة مُفزع.
She says that there is nothing more sensual
قالت: “لا يوجد شيء أكثر حسيّة
than a hot shower,
من الاستحمام بماء ساخن،
that every drop of water
فكل قطرة ماء
is a blessing to the senses.
هي نعمة للحواس”.
She doesn't see herself as disabled.
لم تنظر لنفسها كمعاقة.
In her mind, she's still surfing in the ocean.
لا تزال تركب الأمواج -في عقلها-
Ethel Seiderman, a feisty, beloved activist
إيثيل سيدرمان ناشطة محبوبة ومشاكسة،
in the place where I live in California.
في المكان الذي أعيش فيه في كاليفورنيا.
She wears red patent shoes,
ترتدي حذاء أحمر ساطِع.
and her mantra is that one scarf is nice
وشعارها: “وشاح واحد يكون جيد،
but two is better.
لكن اثنان يكونان أفضل”.
She has been a widow for nine years,
كانت أرملة لمدة تسع سنوات.
but she's not looking for another mate.
لكنها لم تبحث عن رفيق آخر.
She says that there is only a limited number
تقول "يوجد عدد محدود
of ways you can screw —
من الطرق لتمارس الجنس."
well, she says it in another way —
حسنا، قالت ذلك بطريقة أخرى.
and she has tried them all.
وهي جرَّبت جميع الطرق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I, on the other hand,
من ناحية أُخرى،
I still have erotic fantasies with Antonio Banderas —
لازالت لديّ تخيلات مثيرة مع أنطونيو بانديراس
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
and my poor husband has to put up with it.
وزوجي المسكيين عليه أن يتحَّمل هذا.
So how can I stay passionate?
إذا كيف أبقى عاطفية؟
I cannot will myself to be passionate at 71.
أنا لا أستطيع أن أجعل نفسي عاطفية في عمري الواحد والسبعين.
I have been training for some time,
لقد تدربت لبعض الوقت.
and when I feel flat and bored, I fake it.
وعند إحساسي بالملل والضيق، أزيف شعوري.
Attitude, attitude.
السلوك ثم السلوك.
How do I train? I train by saying yes
كيف أتدرب؟ من خلال قول “نعم”
to whatever comes my way:
تجاه أي أمر يواجهني:
drama, comedy, tragedy,
الدراما والكوميديا والتراجيديا،
love, death, losses.
الحب والموت والخسارة.
Yes to life.
نعم للحياة.
And I train by trying to stay in love.
وأتدرب عن طريق بقائي في قصة حب.
It doesn't always work,
هذا لا يعمل دائمًاـ
but you cannot blame me for trying.
لكنك لا تستطيع أن تلومني على المحاولة.
And, on a final note,
والملاحظة الأخيرة،
retirement in Spanish is jubilación.
التقاعد في اللغة الإسبانية jubilación
Jubilation. Celebration.
ابتهاج. احتفال.
We have paid our dues.
لقد دفعنا مستحقاتنا.
We have contributed to society.
ساهمنا في المجتمع.
Now it's our time, and it's a great time.
الآن، حان وقتنا، وهو وقت عظيم.
Unless you are ill or very poor,
لديك اختيارات،
you have choices.
إلا إذا كنت مريضًا أو فقيرًا.
I have chosen to stay passionate,
لقد اخترت أن أبقى عاطفية،
engaged with an open heart.
تعهدت بهذا بقلب صريح.
I am working on it every day.
أعمل على هذا كل يوم.
Want to join me?
أتريدوا مشاركتي؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
June Cohen: So Isabel — IA: Thank you.
جون كوهن: حسنا إيزابيل - إيزابيل: شكرًا لكم.
JC: First of all,
جون: قبل كل شيء،
I never like to presume to speak for the TED community,
لا أحب أبدًا أن أفترض أنني أتحدث باسم جمهور TED
but I would like to tell you that I have a feeling
ولكني أُريد أن أُخبرك بأن لديّ شعور
we can all agree that you are still charming,
جميعنا نتفق عليه بأنك لازلت جذّابة،
seductive and sexy. Yes?
مُغرية، مثيرة، أليس كذلك؟
IA: Aww, thank you. (Applause)
إيزابيل: أوو شكرا لك. (تصفيق)
JC: Hands down. IA: No, it's makeup.
جون: دون نقاش. إيزابيل: إنه المكياج.
Moderator: Now, would it be awkward
جون: هل سيكون من غير الملائم الآن،
if I asked you a follow-up question about your erotic fantasies?
إذا سألتُكِ عن تخيُلاتك المثيرة؟
IA: Oh, of course. About what?
إيزابيبل: بالطبع، عن ماذا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Moderator: About your erotic fantasies. IA: With Antonio Banderas.
جون: عن تخيلاتك المثيرة. إيزابيل: مع أنطونيو بانديراس.
Moderator: I was just wondering if you have anything more to share.
جون: أتساءل فقط، إذا كان لديك المزيد لتخبرينا.
IA: Well, one of them is that — (Laughter)
حسنًا، أحد التخيلات هو الآتي - (ضحك)
One of them is that I place a naked Antonio Banderas
وضعت صورة لأنطونيو بانديراس عاريًا
on a Mexican tortilla,
على التورتيلا المكسيكية،
I slather him with guacamole and salsa,
ودهنتها بالسلطة المكسيكية،
I roll him up, and I eat him. (Laughter)
ولففتها ومن ثم أكلته. (ضحك)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)